# MATTHEW BREHMER, PHD

### DATA VISUALIZATION RESEARCHER



- mattbrehmer@gmail.com
- mabrehme@microsoft.com
- amattbrehmer.github.io
- **aka.ms**/mabrehme
- **▼ twitter**/mattbrehmer
- in linkedin/matthewbrehmer
- **S** skype/matthewbrehmer
- github/mattbrehmer
- **iii** bl.ocks/mattbrehmer

I am a postdoctoral researcher at **Microsoft Research** in Redmond, Washington, where I specialize in expressive information visualization design and data visualization for mobile devices. I am a member of the EPIC (Extended Perception, Interaction & Cognition) and Human Computer Interaction groups, and I am affiliated with Microsoft's Data Journalism Program.

### **EXPERTISE**

#### VISUALIZATION AND INTERFACE DESIGN

I design, develop, and deploy visualization tools and techniques for data analysis and communication.

- → EXAMPLES PROJECTS: Timeline Storyteller, Portfolio Sandbox, SoundConsensus, ShinyFork
- → RELATED PUBLICATIONS: J6, J5, T3

#### QUANTITATIVE HUMAN FACTORS RESEARCH

I conduct controlled experiments as a way to understand human capabilities with respect to perception and attention with the objective of deriving actionable implications for interface design.

→ RELATED PUBLICATIONS: C6, C4, T2, C3, T1

#### QUALITATIVE HUMAN FACTORS RESEARCH

I evaluate current data analysis and communication processes, work-in-progress designs, and deployed visualization tools by means of work domain analyses, interviews, chauffeured walkthroughs, and field studies.

→ RELATED PUBLICATIONS: J5, J2, W3, W2, TR1, T2

### APPLICATION DOMAINS

### DATA JOURNALISM AND STORYTELLING

I aim to provide journalists and storytellers with usable and expressive tools for presenting information visually to their audience, such as with tools like *Timeline Storyteller*, *TimeLineCurator*, and *ChartAccent*.

→ RELATED PUBLICATIONS: J4, J6

My PhD research included case studies of journalists who used Overview to investigate and report on large text document collections. Our findings provided transferable lessons for visualizing analyzing document collections and hierarchical data.

→ RELATED PUBLICATION: |2

# APPLICATION DOMAINS (CONT.)

#### **ENERGY MANAGEMENT AND CONSERVATION**

My PhD research included the design and development of visualization prototypes for analyzing and monitoring energy usage in portfolios of commercial buildings. I consulted with various stakeholders and prospective users, envisioning and implementing designs for interactively locating patterns and anomalies.

→ RELATED PUBLICATION: J5

#### **HEALTH AND FITNESS**

My MSc research pertained to the design and evaluation of *C-TOC*, a computerized cognitive assessment tool intended for early detection of dementia. I studied the use of *C-TOC* prototypes by healthy older adults and by adults with diagnosed mild cognitive impairments.

→ RELATED PUBLICATIONS: C4, J3, T2, W1

Prior to my MSc, I worked in the area of exercise video games (aka active games): I studied the role of physical exertion on cognitive task performance. I also developed *GAIM*, an XNA/C# toolkit which allowed players with different input peripherals to play active games together.

→ RELATED PUBLICATIONS: C2, C1, T1

### **EDUCATION**

### DOCTOR OF PHILOSOPHY, COMPUTER SCIENCE

2011 - 2016

University of British Columbia (UBC), Vancouver, Canada

- → THESIS: Why Visualization? Task Abstraction for Analysis and Design
- → SUPERVISORY COMMITTEE: Tamara Munzner (UBC Computer Science), Joanna McGrenere (UBC Computer Science), and Ronald A. Rensink (UBC Psychology)
- → EXAMINATION COMMITTEE: Jason Dykes (giCentre, City University London), Alfred Hermida (UBC Journalism), and Giuseppe Carenini (UBC Computer Science)
- → RELATED PUBLICATIONS: T3, J1, J2, J5, TR1, W2

### MASTER OF SCIENCE, COMPUTER SCIENCE

2009 - 2011

Specialization in Human-Computer Interaction University of British Columbia (UBC), Vancouver, Canada

- → THESIS: Usability and the Effects of Interruption in C-TOC: Self-
- Administered Cognitive Testing on a Computer
- → SUPERVISED BY: Joanna McGrenere (UBC Computer Science) and Claudia Jacova (UBC Medicine)
- → THESIS READER: Peter Graf (UBC Psychology)
- → RELATED PUBLICATIONS: C4, J3, W1, T2

# EDUCATION (CONT.)

# BACHELOR OF COMPUTING 2004 - 2009

Specialization in Cognitive Science with Professional Internship Queen's University, Kingston, Canada

- → THESIS: Assessing the Effect of Exercise Intensity on Cognitive Task Performance in an Exercise Video Game
- → THESIS ADVISER: T.C. Nicholas Graham (Queen's School of Computing)
- → RELATED PUBLICATION: T1

# **EMPLOYMENT HISTORY**

Microsoft Research Postdoctoral Researcher Redmond, USA	2016 - PRESENT
<b>University of British Columbia</b> Department of Computer Science Graduate Research Assistant Vancouver, Canada	2009 - 2016
Microsoft Research Graduate Research Intern Redmond, USA	2015
Pulse Energy (now a division of EnerNOC) Mitacs Graduate Research Intern Vancouver, Canada	2013 - 2014
<b>University of British Columbia</b> Department of Computer Science Graduate Teaching Assistant Vancouver, Canada	2009 - 2011
<b>Queen's University</b> School of Computing Research Assitant Kingston, Canada	2009
<b>EMC Corporation</b> (now Dell EMC) User Interface Design Intern Toronto, Canada	2007 - 2008
Killam Properties, Inc. Information Technology Staff and Web Developer Halifax, Canada	2006

MATTHEW BREHMER | CURRICULUM VITAE | LAST UPDATED: Aug 2018

# **INVITED TALKS**

Slides and videos from these talks are available at mattbrehmer.github.io/#talks

Timeline Storyteller, from Visualization Design Space to Deployment The University of Calgary Data Empowerment Speaker Series (Calgary, Canada)	2018 / 06 / 18
Data-Driven Storytelling at Microsoft: Introducing Timeline Storyteller and ChartAccent for Microsoft Power Bl  UBC School of Journalism Course on Special Topics in Contemporary Journalism: Data Viz (JRNL 520H) (Vancouver, Canada)	2017 / 10 / 24
Timelines Revisited: A Design Space and Considerations for Expressive Storytelling IEEE InfoVis 2017 (Phoenix, USA)  → RELATED PUBLICATION: J6	2017 / 10 / 03
Expressive Storytelling With Timelines Uber Visualization Night: A Journey Through Space and Time (Seattle, USA)	2017 / 08 / 31
Timelines Revisited: Considerations for Expressive Storytelling King's College London Department of Informatics (London, UK)	2017/07/11
Timelines Revisited: Considerations for Expressive Storytelling City University London giCentre (London, UK)	2017/07/10
The Timeline Storyteller Custom Visual for Power BI Microsoft Data Insights Summit BI Power Hour (Seattle, USA)	2017 / 06 / 13
Timelines Revisited: Considerations for Expressive Storytelling Northeastern University NUVis Visualization Consortium (Boston, USA)	2017 / 04 / 28
<i>Timelines Revisited: Considerations for Expressive Storytelling</i> Bentley University RealViz talk series (Waltham, USA)	2017 / 04 / 27
What Story Does Your Timeline Tell? OpenVisConf 2017 (Boston, USA)	2017 / 04 / 24
Timelines Revisited: Considerations for Expressive Storytelling Radcliffe Institute at Harvard University (Cambridge, USA)	2016/12/08
Why Visualization? Task Abstraction for Analysis and Design Dissertation Defence (Vancouver, Canada)  → RELATED PUBLICATION: T3	2016 / 03 / 23
Storytelling with Timeline Data Data-Driven Storytelling Dagstuhl Seminar (Wadern, Germany)	2016 / 02 / 11

Why Visualization? Task Abstraction for Analysis and Design Microsoft Research (Redmond, USA)	2016 / 02 / 01
Matches, Mismatches, and Methods: Multiple-View Workflows for Energy Portfolio Analysis IEEE InfoVis 2015 (Chicago, USA)  → RELATED PUBLICATION: J5	2015 / 10 / 28
Matches, Mismatches, and Methods: Multiple-View Workflows for Energy Portfolio Analysis University of Washington (Seattle, USA)	2015 / 09 / 04
The Future of Data and Design In Visualization Research Vancouver Data Visualization Meetup (Vancouver, Canada)	2015 / 05 / 19
Overview: The Design, Adoption, and Analysis of a Visual Document Mining Tool For Investigative Journalists IEEE InfoVis 2014 (Paris, France)  → RELATED PUBLICATION: J2	2014/11/14
Visualizing Dimensionally-Reduced Data: Interviews with Analysts and a Characterization of Task Sequences ACM BELIV 2014 (Paris, France) → RELATED PUBLICATION: W3	2014/11/10
Pre-Design Empiricism for Information Visualization: Scenarios, Methods, and Challenges  ACM BELIV 2014 (Paris, France)  → RELATED PUBLICATION: W2	2014 / 11 / 10
Visualization Task Abstraction from Multiple Perspectives IEEE VIS Doctoral Colloquium 2014 (Paris, France)	2014 / 11 / 08
A Multi-Level Typology of Abstract Visualization Tasks IEEE InfoVis 2013 (Atlanta, USA)  → RELATED PUBLICATION: J1	2013/10/15
Investigating Interruptions in the Context of Computerised Cognitive Testing for Older Adults ACM CHI 2012 (Austin, USA) → RELATED PUBLICATION: C4	2012 / 05 / 10
A Tale of Two Studies: Investigating the Impact of Interruptions on Task Performance in Older Adults GRAND NCE AGM 2011 (Vancouver, Canada) → RELATED PUBLICATION: W1	2011 / 05 / 14

### **PUBLICATIONS**

Author copies of these publications are available at mattbrehmer.github.io/#pubs

PUBLICATION TYPES: J = journal article, c = conference proceedings, w = workshop paper, вc = book chapter, T = thesis, PO = poster.

#### PUBLICATIONS AS PRIMARY AUTHOR

# ]8 Visualizing Ranges over Time on Mobile Phones: A Task-Based Crowdsourced Evaluation Matthew Brehmer, Bongshin Lee, Petra Isenberg, and Eun Kyoung Choe To appear in Volume 25, Issue 1 (Jan. 2019) of IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics (InfoVis 2018). BC1 Evaluating Data-Driven Stories & Storytelling Tools Fereshteh Amini\*, Matthew Brehmer\*, Gordon Bolduan, Christina Elmer, and Benjamin Wiederkehr (\* equal contribution) A chapter in Data-Driven Storytelling, a book edited by Sheelagh Carpendale, Nicholas Diakopoulos, Christophe Hurter, and Nathalie Henry Riche, 2018. Po1 Demonstrating the Value of Visualization: Highlights from the 2017 PacificVis Visual Data Storytelling Contest Matthew Brehmer, Kyungwon Lee, Ivan Viola, Jinwook Seo, and Bongshin Lee. In poster proceedings of the 2017 IEEE VIS Conference. Timelines Revisited: J6 A Design Space and Considerations for Expressive Storytelling Matthew Brehmer, Bongshin Lee, Benjamin Bach, Nathalie Henry Riche, and Tamara Munzner In Volume 23, Issue 9 (Sept. 2017) of IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics.

T3

J5

12

# Why Visualization? Task Abstraction for Analysis and Design **Matthew Brehmer**

University of British Columbia PhD Dissertation (April, 2016).

Matches, Mismatches, and Methods: Multiple-View Workflows for Energy Portfolio Analysis Matthew Brehmer, Jocelyn Ng, Kevin Tate, and Tamara Munzner In Volume 22, Issue 1 (Jan. 2016) of IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics (InfoVis 2015).

Overview: The Design, Adoption, and Analysis of a Visual Document Mining Tool For Investigative Journalists

Matthew Brehmer, Stephen Ingram, Jonathan Stray, and Tamara Munzner. In Volume 20, Issue 12 (Dec. 2014) of IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics (InfoVis 2014).

# PUBLICATIONS (CONT.)

Visualizing Dimensionally-Reduced Data: Interviews with Analysts and a Characterization of Task Sequences Matthew Brehmer, Michael Sedlmair, Stephen Ingram, and Tamara Munzner In proceedings of the 2014 ACM BELIV Workshop (Beyond Time and Errors: Novel Evaluation Methods for Visualization).	W3
Pre-Design Empiricism for Information Visualization: Scenarios, Methods, and Challenges Matthew Brehmer, Sheelagh Carpendale, Bongshin Lee, and Melanie Tory. In proceedings of the 2014 ACM BELIV Workshop (Beyond Time and Errors: Novel Evaluation Methods for Visualization).	W2
A Multi-Level Typology of Abstract Visualization Tasks Matthew Brehmer and Tamara Munzner In Volume 19, Issue 12 (Dec. 2013) of IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics (InfoVis 2013).	J1
Investigating Interruptions in the Context of Computerised Cognitive Testing for Older Adults  Matthew Brehmer, Joanna McGrenere, Charlotte Tang, and Claudia Jacova In proceedings of the 2012 ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI).	C4
Usability and the Effects of Interruption in C-TOC: Self-Administered Cognitive Testing on a Computer Matthew Brehmer University of British Columbia MSc Thesis (2011).	T2
A Tale of Two Studies: Investigating the Impact of Interruptions on Task Performance in Older Adults  Matthew Brehmer, Charlotte Tang, Joanna McGrenere, and Claudia Jacova In the work-in-progress proceedings of the the 2011 GRAND NCE AGM.	W1
Activate Your GAIM: A Toolkit for Input in Active Games Matthew Brehmer, Nicholas Graham, and Tadeusz Stach In proceedings of the 2010 ACM Future Play Conference.	C2
Assessing the Effect of Exercise Intensity on Cognitive Task Performance in an Exercise Video Game Matthew Brehmer Queen's University B.Comp Thesis (2009).	T1

# **CO-AUTHORED PUBLICATIONS**

J7	Charticulator: Interactive Construction of Bespoke Chart Layouts Donghao Ren, Bongshin Lee, and Matthew Brehmer
	To appear in Volume 25, Issue 1 (Jan. 2019) of <i>IEEE Transactions on Visualization</i>
	and Computer Graphics (InfoVis 2018).
	[Best Paper Honorable Mention Award]
W5	Reflecting on the Evaluation of Visualization Authoring Systems
	Donghao Ren, Bongshin Lee, <b>Matthew Brehmer</b> , and Nathalie Henry Riche
	To appear the workshop proceedings of <i>BELIV 2018: Evaluation and Beyond - Methodological Approaches for Visualization</i> .
	wiethodological Approaches for visualization.
C6	What's the Difference?:
	Evaluating Variants of Multi-Series Bar Charts for Visual Comparison Tasks  Arjun Srinivasan, Matthew Brehmer, Bongshin Lee, and Steven Drucker  In proceedings of the 2018 ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing  Systems (CHI).
W4	Data Visualization on Mobile Devices
***	Bongshin Lee, <b>Matthew Brehmer</b> , Eun Kyoung Choe, Petra Isenberg, Ricardo
	Langer, and Raimund Dachselt
	In extended abstract proceedings of the 2018 ACM Conference on Human
	Factors in Computing Systems (CHI).
C5	ChartAccent: Annotation for Data-Driven Storytelling
	Donghao Ren, <b>Matthew Brehmer</b> , Bongshin Lee, Tobias Höllerer, and Eun
	Kyoung Choe
	In proceedings of the 2017 <i>IEEE PacificVis Symposium</i> .
J4	TimeLineCurator:
	Interactive Authoring of Visual Timelines from Unstructured Text
	Johanna Fulda, <b>Matthew Brehmer</b> , and Tamara Munzner
	In Volume 22, Issue 1 (Jan. 2016) of <i>IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics (VAST 2015)</i> .
J3	C-TOC (Cognitive Testing on Computer):
	Investigating the Usability and Validity of a Novel Self-administered
	Cognitive Assessment Tool in Aging and Early Dementia Claudia Jacova, Joanna McGrenere, Hyunsoo S. Lee, William Wang, Sarah Le
	Huray, Emily F. Corenblith, <b>Matthew Brehmer</b> , Charlotte Tang, Sherri Hayden, B.
	Lynn Beattie, and Ging-Yuek R. Hsiung
	In <i>Alzheimer Disease and Associated Disorders</i> (July 2015).
	Dimensionality Reduction in the Wild: Gaps and Guidance
TR1	Difficilitionality reduction in the rimal caps and calculate
TR1	Michael Sedlmair, <b>Matthew Brehmer</b> , Stephen Ingram, and Tamara Munzner

# CO-AUTHORED PUBLICATIONS (CONT.)

### The Haptic Crayola Effect:

Exploring the Role of Naming in Learning Haptic Stimuli

Inwook Hwang, Karon MacLean, **Matthew Brehmer**, Jeff Hendy, Andreas Sotirkopoulos, and Seungmoon Choi

In proceedings of the 2011 IEEE World Haptics Conference.

### Classifying Input for Active Games

C1

C3

Tadeusz Stach, Nicholas Graham, **Matthew Brehmer**, Andreas Hollatz In proceedings of the 2009 *ACM Advances in Computer Entertainment Technology (ACE) Conference*.

### ACADEMIC SERVICE

**Organizing Committee**: IEEE VIS 2018 (Co-Chair: Visualization in Practice), the Data Visualization on Mobile Devices Workshop at CHI 2018, IEEE PacificVis 2017-2018 (Co-Chair, Visual Data Storytelling Contest)

**Program Committee**: IEEE InfoVis (2017, 2018), EuroVis State of the Art Reports (2017), IEEE PacificVis (2017, 2018), FAT\*: Conference on Fairness, Accountability, and Transparency (2018), The Art of Networks III (2018), VIS Arts Program (2018), Information+ (2018), BELIV: Evaluation and Beyond - Methodological Approaches for Visualization (2018), Computation + Journalism (2019)

**Reviewer:** IEEE InfoVis (2013 - 2016), IEEE VAST (2015), IEEE PacificVis (2017), IEEE TVCG (2015 - 2018), EuroVis (2014 - 2017), ACM CHI (2013 - 2018), ACM TOCHI (2013), Sage Information Visualization Journal (2015 - 2016), ACM SIGGRAPH Asia (2012), GRAND NCE ACM (2012)

Student Volunteer: ACM CHI Conference (2011, 2013, 2015, 2016)

# **UNIVERSITY SERVICE**

University of Washington: Invited Project Judge for CSE 442 Data Visualization (2017)

University of British Columbia Department of Computer Science: Graduate Admissions and Recruitment Committee (2013-2015), Guest Lecturer (CPSC 547: Information Visualization, 2014-2017), Curriculum Development (CPSC 444: Advanced Human Computer Interaction Methods, 2010-2011), Teaching Assistant (CPSC 444: Advanced Human Computer Interaction Methods, 2010; CPSC 344: Introduction to Human Computer Interaction Methods, 2009)

University of British Columbia Computer Science Graduate Students' Association: Vice President (Social Affairs) (2010-2011), Graduate Student Orientation Committee (2012), Organizer of the Un-Distinguished Lecture Series (2010–2011, 2012–2013)

**Queen's University Computing Students' Association**: Student Orientation Leader (2005), First Year Representative (2004-2005)

# **AWARDS**

University of British Columbia: Student Service Award (2016), Volunteering Award (2015), Mitacs-Accelerate Graduate Research Internship Program Award (2013-2014), Natural Sciences & Engineering Research Council of Canada (NSERC) Postgraduate Scholarship (2011-2014), Four Year Doctoral Fellowship (2011-2015), Department of Computer Science Merit Scholarship (2009-2011)

**Queen's University**: Dean's Entrance Scholarship in Computing (2004-2005)

# **REFERENCES**

References are available upon request.